Joel Martin Halpern collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Joel Martin Halpern collection 1870-2000 1950-1990
AFC 1998/001
Halpern, Joel M. (Joel Martin), 1929-2019; Kerewsky-Halpern, Barbara
approximately 3,100 items
21 containers
12 linear feet
approximately 720 documents (approximately 4,750 sheets)
16 sound cassettes: analog
28 sound tape reels: analog; 5 in. and 7 in.
approximately 2,005 photocopies of photographs: black and white; various sizes
126 photographs: prints, black and white; 5 x 7 in.
57 photographs: prints, color; 3.5 x 5 and 4 x 6 in.
54 photographs: negatives, color; 35 mm
37 photographs: transparencies, color; 35 mm
26 plates: color
20 drawings: ink, black and white
1 drawing: ink and paint, color
8 videocassettes (VHS): analog; 1/2 in.
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The Joel Martin Halpern Collection consists of various types of materials, both published and unpublished, related to the Halpern's ethnographic fieldwork and documentation of folk cultures in Eastern Europe, as well as their work with South Slavs in Ontario, Canada (Series 1) and Southeast Asia (Series 2). In addition, the collection includes Joel Martin Halpern's work in Alaska and Arctic Canada among the Inuit (Series 3), and miscellaneous manuscripts (Series 4).
Provenance
Joel Martin Halpern; Donation; 1997-2000.
Custodial History
Since November 1997, Joel Martin Halpern has donated a substantial amount of materials related to his and his wife's ethnographic fieldwork to the American Folklife Center. Prior to arriving at the Library of Congress, a portion of this collection (33 audio recordings) was stored at The Amherst College Library. Upon Professor Halpern's request, these materials were deaccessioned in 1997, and he donated them to the American Folklife Center. Furthermore, 126 black-and-white photographs (see Box 13) were given to Joel Martin Halpern by the Ethnographic Museum in Sofia, Bulgaria in exchange for anthropology textbooks. Some of the unprocessed accruals to this collection will become part of other collections.
Accruals
Multiple unprocessed accruals are held at the American Folklife Center.
Transfers
256 commercial recordings, as well as a Yugoslavian record label catalog and its supplement, were transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division at the Library of Congress.
Photocopies of three conference papers on Vietnamese themes, not authored by the Halperns, were added to the Folklife Reading Room's subject file.
558 published works, primarily on ethnographic themes relating to the Balkans, were transferred to the Acquisitions or the Selection Officer of the East European Division for addition to the general collection. Copies of the title pages of these volumes are on file in this collection.
Consult a reference librarian in the Folklife Reading Room for specific information.
Access and Restrictions
The Joel Martin Halpern collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Notes
Joel Martin Halpern
Joel Martin Halpern was born April 8, 1929, in New York City. Halpern received a B.A. in History from the University of Michigan in 1950, and in 1956 earned his Ph.D. in anthropology from Columbia University. He started his teaching career in 1955 as a lecturer in anthropology at Columbia; he then served as assistant professor of anthropology at the University of California, Los Angeles, from 1958 to 1963, and as associate professor of anthropology at Brandeis University from 1963 to 1965. From 1965 to 1967 Halpern was an associate at the Harvard University Russian Research Center. From 1967 until his retirement in 1992, he was first associate professor and then professor of anthropology at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. His ethnographic research has been supported by grants from the National Science Foundation, the National Institutes of Health, the State Department, the Canadian Government, the National Academy of Sciences, the International Research and Exchanges Board (IREX), and the National Endowment for the Humanities, as well as by the University of California at Los Angeles and the University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
Throughout his career, Halpern has traveled widely and conducted extensive field research. In the summer of 1950, he studied Eskimo settlements on the Seward Peninsula of Alaska. In 1953-54 and during several other times throughout his career (1961-62, 1964, 1978, 1986), Halpern, and his wife traveled to and resided in various parts of the former Yugoslavia, where they studied Serbian village folklife. In the mid-1950s, the Halperns also conducted fieldwork in Laos, while visiting Thailand and Vietnam. At that time, Halpern was employed as a Field Service Officer with the Community Development Division of USOM (the American aid mission). He returned on research trips to Laos in 1959 and 1969. Other research trips took him to Sweden, the Soviet Union, Greece, Israel, India, Bulgaria, and Canada. Although he conducted research in various global locations, the majority of the primary source materials in this collection was gathered in Yugoslavia, Laos, and Canada.
Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern
Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern was born in 1931. She received her B.A. in geography-geology from Barnard College in 1953, her M.A. in linguistics, and her Ph.D. in anthropology from the University of Massachusetts, Amherst, in 1979. Initially, her career focused on socio-linguistics, though she later specialized in medical anthropology. During her career, Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern has served a research associate and adjunct professor at the University of Massachusetts. She has traveled and lectured in Australia, India, Pakistan, and Hungary among other areas. In 1974, she conducted fieldwork among South Slavic Canadians in Ontario under the auspices of the Canadian Museum of Civilization. Her research was supported by the National Science Foundation and the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Scope and Content
The Joel Martin Halpern Collection consists of photographs, slides, photocopies of photographs, photocopies of articles, audiotapes, videocassettes, published book materials, texts in native languages, manuscripts, reproductions of visual images, and ephemera related to his ethnographic field documentation undertaken from 1949 to 2000 in Asia, Europe, and North America. The materials were assembled by Joel Martin Halpern, professor emeritus of anthropology at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst, and by his wife and colleague Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern. The Halperns conducted their fieldwork primarily from the 1950s to the 1990s, principally in the area of the former Yugoslavia, as well as in other areas of the Balkans. Their most intensive fieldwork was among the Serbs. In addition to this work, Joel Halpern conducted his own ethnographic research among Laotian, Vietnamese, and Inuit ethnic groups. The research materials in this collection emphasize historic aspects of folk culture. This includes documentation of material culture, such as architecture, agricultural implements, household utensils, and costume, as well as intellectual culture, such as music within the context of peasant tradition and village folk beliefs, and oral tradition in the setting of kinship structures and the structure of community social organization.
Much of the primary source material of this collection consists of photographs of Balkan areas, especially Serbian and Bulgarian villages. There is also a series of sound recordings of music and interviews with Serbians and Bulgarians (see tape logs), as well as a collection of folklore programs recorded from Sofia radio, plus videocassettes of Bosnian and Serbian rural life. In addition there are interviews with Canadian Inuit people and tapes from the Inuit Broadcasting Corporation recorded from broadcasts in the Baffin Island area.
Manuscript and photograph dates in the Container List usually refer to publication or photography dates; the collection contains many photocopies, with some originals.
Arrangement
The Joel Martin Halpern collection is organized in four series:
Administrative files
Series 1: Eastern European materials, 1870-1999
Series 2: Southeast Asian materials, 1957-2000
Series 3: Inuit materials, 1952-2000
Series 4: Miscellaneous materials, 1943-1996
Collection documentation and donor biographical information which was listed in Series 1 in a previous version of the finding aid have been moved to "Administrative Files" in this finding aid.
Videos with two or more subjects which were listed in Series 5 in a previous version of this finding aid have instead been listed in "Administrative Files" in this finding aid.
Oversize items listed in Series 2, Subseries 5 in a previous version of the finding aid have been incorporated into Series 1, Subseries 1 and Series 1, Subseries 3 in this finding aid.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Halpern, Joel M. (Joel Martin), 1929-2019, collector.; Kerewsky-Halpern, Barbara, collector.
Organizations
American Folklife Center.; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Albanians--Social life and customs.; Bosnians--Social life and customs.; Bulgarians--Social life and customs.; Croats--Social life and customs.; Ethnology--Balkan Peninsula.; Ethnology--Serbia.; Ethnology--Slovenia.; Ethnology--Southeast Asia.; Ethnology--Yugoslavia.; Folk songs, Bulgarian--Bulgaria.; Folk songs, Lao.; Folk songs, Serbian--Serbia.; Inuit--Canada--Social life and customs.; Laotian Americans--Social life and customs.; Laotians--Social life and customs.; Serbs--Social life and customs.; Slovenes--Social life and customs.; Vietnamese Americans--Social life and customs.
Places
Orašac (Serbia)--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Container List
- Administrative files
  - Collection documentation
    - Collection guide and inventories, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Collection correspondence, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Inventories by format
    - Black-and-white photo inventory, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Color photo inventory, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Halpern text and published text inventory, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Tape log and inventory, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Video log and inventory, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Supplemental video information, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Biographical information, research interests, and notes, 1958-1996
    - Joel Martin Halpern, 1975-1996
    - Being an Anthropologist, part 1, April 1992, AFC 1998/001: MV01; Joel Martin Halpern, Richard D. Holmes, Department of Anthropology, University of Massachusetts at Amherst; AFC 1998/001: VT001; 1 videocassette (120 minutes)
      Discussion by Joel Martin Halpern of his career as an anthropologist. Note on media: "#1: 4/92. Autobiography; Alaska-Eskimo '50; Yugoslavia '53-'54; Laos '57"
    - Being an Anthropologist, part 2, April 1992, AFC 1998/001: MV02; Joel Martin Halpern, Richard D. Holmes, Department of Anthropology, University of Massachusetts at Amherst; AFC 1998/001: VT002; 1 videocassette (120 minutes)
      Discussion by Joel Martin Halpern of his career as an anthropologist. Note on media: "#2: Inuit Drum Dance; Far East Comes Near; JMH video Orasac; Being an Anthrop. part 2"
      - Copies of 1984 and 1996 curriculum vitae; Publications bibliography in Anthropology of Eastern Europe. Annual Review of Anthropology 12 (1983): 397; 1980 Contemporary Authors website entry; undated Contemporary Authors entry in New Revision Series Vol. 3, 1984-1996, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Field notes, 1975, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Notes on Albert B. Lord lecture, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, 1958-1991
      - Copies of 1976, 1980, 1984, 1987, 1989, and 1991 curriculum vitae; undated abbreviated curriculum vitae; 1958 brochure describing available slide lectures, 1976-1991, 1958, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Graduate student course notes in linguistics, 1971-1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Participation in International Slavic Seminar, Serbia, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Notes on Noam Chomsky lecture, University of Massachusetts, 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Notes and program from A Conference on Folklore in New York City, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/15)
      - "Bulgarian Notes," 1975, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Notes and research on drug and alcohol abuse., undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Joel Martin Halpern and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, 1980
      - Participation in Northeastern Anthropological Association Conference; correspondence, paper abstracts, complete papers, conference program; Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern's personal notes from conference. Joint paper dealing with the research of Polish anthropologist Jozef Obrebski in Macedonia, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 2/16)
- Series 1: Eastern European materials, 1870-1999
  - Subseries 1: Manuscript materials, 1915-1998, Dates in this series usually refer to publication dates; the collection contains many photocopies of publications, with some originals.
    - Correspondence, 1974-1981
      - Letters from the American Museum of Natural History to Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, January and June; note from Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern, 1974, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/20)
      - Letters from Zivomir Mladenovic, May-June 1976, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/21)
      - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies Newsletter 20, no. 2 (Summer 1980); Letter from Elliott Mossman to Professor Lj. D. Popovich. January 1980; Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern correspondence, Winter-Summer 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/22)
      - Letter to Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern from Barbara Lex, March 1981, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/23)
      - Letter to Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern from Judith Friedman, with submission guidelines for articles to Natural History, June 1981, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/24)
      - Letter from Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern to American Museum of Natural History (AMNH); letter from Thomas Cook Travel to Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern; letter from Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern to Thomas Cook Travel regarding on board lecturer for AMNH Mediterranean Cruise; index card of notes, June-July 1981, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Joel Martin Halpern: Unpublished texts, 1961
      - Coding Instructions for Yugoslav Interviews:1-55, 1961, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/26)
      - Yugoslavia (NSF) Project description: 1-2, 1961, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/27)
    - Joel Martin Halpern: Published texts, 1989-1996
      - Halpern, Joel Martin and Andrei Simic. A Case Study from Rural Serbia (Yugoslavia). International Area Studies Programs at Amherst 20: 18 pages, 1989, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/28)
      - Halpern, Joel Martin. Sociocultural Processes and Kinds of Time: A Perspective on Rural Change in Bulgaria. International Area Studies at Amherst 21: 1-9, 1989, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/29)
      - Wagner, Richard A. (with an introduction by Joel Martin Halpern) Children and Change in Orasac, 1870-1975: A Serbian Perspective on Fertility Decline. Program in Soviet and East European Studies: Occasional Paper Series No. 22, University of Massachusetts at Amherst: 52 pages, 1992, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/30)
      - Kaser, Karl, and Joel Martin Halpern. Contemporary Research on the Balkan Family: Anthropological and Historical Approaches. Rapports / 7me Congrès International D'Etudes du Sud-Est Européen, Comité National Grec des Etudes Sud-Est Européen, Athens: 103-32, 1994, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/31)
      - Martin, Joel Martin, and Slavko Kremensek. Etnoloko-Antropolosko Dopisovanje, Ethnological-Anthropological Correspondence. Glasnik Slovenkega Etnoloskega Drustva: Bulletin of Slovene Ethnological Society 35, no. 2-3 (October 1995): 45-55, 1995, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/32)
      - Observations on a War: The Conflict in Bosnia (Part 1 of 2). Anthrowatch 4, no. 1, (May 1996): 7-8, 1996, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/33)
    - Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Unpublished texts, 1972-1979
      - Thoughts on Communicative Competence in a Serbian Village: 24 pages, 1972, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/34)
      - Ritual Roles of Women in a Patriarchal Society-The Serbian Case: 9 pages, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/35)
      - Kerewsky-Halpern, Barbara. 'Yonder Comes a Red Hen... ': Mothers and Mother Figures in Serbian Folk Curing: 8 pages. Abstract and correspondence with Women and Folklore Conference coordinator included, 1979, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/36)
      - Kerewsky-Halpern, Barbara, and John M. Foley, Research on Oral Traditional Expression in Sumadija and its Relevance to the Study of Other Oral Traditions.: 199-236, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/37)
    - Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Published texts, 1978-1983
      - Book review: The Wedding of Smailagic Meho. Balkan Studies 19: 215-17, 1978, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/38)
      - Metaphrasis in Contemporary Bulgarian Oral Tradition. Paper presented at the Section V, First Congress of Bulgarian Studies, Sofia, May 23-June 3, 1981 (includes Barbara-Kerewsky Halpern's notes). Published in Culture (Bulgarian publication): 333-45, 1983, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/39)
    - Joel Martin Halpern and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Unpublished texts, 1956
      - Songs and Chants from a Serbian Village: 14 pages, 1956, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/40)
    - Joel Martin Halpern and Barbara Kerewsky-Halpern: Published texts, 1973-1987
      - Obrebski, Joseph. Ritual and Social Structure in a Macedonian Village. Edited by Barbara Kerewsky Halpern, and Joel Martin Halpern. Research Report No. 16: Department of Anthropology, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, May 1977: 21 pages, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/41)
      - Changing Perceptions of Roles as Husbands and Wives in Five Yugoslav Villages Prepared for the 9th International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Chicago, August-September: 21 pages, 1973, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/42)
      - Dugorocna istrajivanja u Orasac ( Long-term Research in Orasac). Pregled 237: Publication of the American Embassy, Belgrade: 84-94, 1987, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 3/43)
    - Monographs and serials by other authors on Balkan topics, Transferred to other LC divisions
      Photocopies of cover pages of books transferred to other Library of Congress divisions.
      - Books, 241 photocopies of book covers and cataloging-in-publication pages (Box-folder 4/44)
      - Books, 220 photocopies of book covers and cataloging-in-publication pages (Box-folder 4/45)
      - Albanian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/46)
      - Bosnian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/47)
      - Bulgarian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/48)
      - Croatian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/49)
      - English monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/50)
      - French monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/51)
      - German monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/52)
      - Hungarian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/53)
      - Macedonian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/54)
      - Polish monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/55)
      - Russian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/56)
      - Serbian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/57)
      - Slovenian monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/58)
      - Other monographs and serials, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 4/59)
        The copies are of books from Belgrade, Serbia and Ljubljana, Slovenia. Originally labeled "Syrian monographs and serials."
    - Publications by other authors categorized by language, 1915-1998
      - South Slavic languages, Selected titles translated into English
        - Nikola Smodlaka publication, 1955, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/60)
        - Poems about Marko, with notes, 1975, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/61)
        - Herald, Bulgarian and other Languages, 1977, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/62)
        - Contrastive Linguistics, 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/63)
        - Bulgarian folk music, 1981, 1983, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/64)
        - How to play folk music, 1984, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/65)
        - Instruments in folklore and culture, 1987, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 5/66)
      - Croatian, Selected titles translated into English
        - Bratanic, Branimir. Croatian Equipment for Plowing Throughout History. Zagreb: Publikacije Etnoloskoga Seminara, 1939, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/67)
        - Gavazzi, Milovan. A Year of Croatian Heritage. (2 vols.) Zabreg: Izdanje Matice Hrvatske, 1939, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/68)
        - Kirin, Vladimir. Narodne Plesovi Jugoslavije (Folk Dances in Yugoslavia) pt. IV Slovenia, Istra, Hrvatsko Primorje. Zagreb: Naklada Nasa Djeca, 1957, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/69)
        - Huzjak, Visnja. Zeleni Jurai (spring custom). Zagreb: Publikacije Etnoloskoga Seminara, 1957, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/70)
        - Kirin, Vladimir. Narodne Plesovi Jugoslavije. pt. V. Zagreb: Naklada Nasa Djeca, 1958, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/71)
        - Stojanovic, Andrija. Handcrafts of Bruestra (Croatia). Zagreb: Publikacije Etnoloskoga Zavoda, 1962, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/72)
        - Vjerni Drugovi (elementary school text). Zagreb: Skolska Kniga, 1963, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/73)
        - Deset Godina: 1959-1969 Ogranka za sr Hrvatsku Etnološkog Društva Jugoslavija, 1969, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 6/74)
        - Folklor i Mi (pamphlet), 1980, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/75)
        - Boskovic-Stulli, Maja. Bajka. Umjetnost Rijeci. Zagreb: Hrvatsko Filososko Drustvo, 1982, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/76)
        - Stankiewicz, Edward. Balkanski i Slovenski Elementi u Judeo-Spanskom Jeziku Jugoslavije: 84-91, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/77)
        - Boskovi-Stulli, Maja. Narodne Pjesme u Okviru Pjesnistva Nob-a: 89-94, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/78)
        - Boskovic-Stulli, Maja. Zene u Slavonskim Narodnim Pjesmama. Ethnographia pannonica, Zena u Seoskoj Kulturi Panonije. Zagreb: Etnoloska Tribina: 75-84, undated, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/79)
      - English
        - Stevenson, Beatrice L. The Gusle Singer and His Songs. American Anthropologist 17: 58-68, 1915, 1 folder of manuscripts (Box-folder 7/80)